Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Industrial Workers of the World PE.044
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Industrial Workers of the World
1905-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
Sherwood, Susan Parker
PE.044
2.75 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 2 shared boxes
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Industrial Workers of the World (1905-2005) is an articial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. It features the publications, pamphlets, news articles, and convention reports of the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW), a labor organization founded in 1905 in Chicago. The IWW fought for increased wages, better working conditions, and fewer hours by attempting to organize workers from all industry lines around the country.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series. Folders are arranged alphabetically within series. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: General Files, 1905-2005
Series II: New York City Branch, 1905-1976
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Industrial Workers of the World (1905-2005) contains materials created by various branches, committies, and member unions of the International Workers of the World.
Series I: General Files, 1905-2005, consists of pamphlets, fliers/leaflets, articles, circular letters, songbooks, and other material from various branches and committees, including the Starbucks Workers Union, Chicago Branch, New York General Membership Branch, Metal and Machinery Workers Union No. 440, and Coal Mine Workers Industrial Union No. 220.
Series II: New York City Branch, 1905-1976, consists of material acquired from the IWW's New York General Membership Branch, which includes various pamphlets, publications, news articles, fliers/leaflets, convention reports, and general records from the General Defense Committee, Centralia Publicity Committee, and One Big Union Workers' Bulletin.
Historical Note
The Industrial Workers of the World (IWW) was founded on June 27, 1905 in Chicago by representatives from 43 groups. The organization was established in response to the wage system of capitalism as well as the organizing methods of the American Federation of Labor. At its founding, the IWW sought to include all industrial workers in order to create One Big Union that would effectively gain better workers' rights, such as increased wages, fewer hours, and improved working conditions. Some of the founding leaders included Daniel De Leon of the Socialist Labor Party, William D. Haywood of the Western Federation of Miners, and Eugene V. Debs of the Socialist Party, who later withdrew his membership as the IWW became more radical. Although often employing militant tactics, the IWW also utilized protest methods that espoused the philosophy of "folded arms" in which they would withhold their labor from employers. Some methods of this included slow downs and massive sickouts. The IWW preferred "striking on the job" over traditional striking and picket lines as workers would often lose their jobs during strikes to scabs. In addition, many IWW members engaged in free speech fights. The IWW encouraged its members to openly recruit new members and voice grievances. They would consequently get arrested and put in jail—costing cities a lot of money. These methods proved effective as free speech bans were often lifted, such as in Spokane, WA in 1909. In 1912, the IWW had an estimated 50,000 members from various industries. In 1923, the IWW saw the height of its membership with roughly 100,000 members. In 1924, the IWW suffered a split due to two differing organizing visions, that of the centralists and the decentralists. The centralists called for the universalization of the IWW, eventually resulting in the IWW taking over the functions of the federal government. Meanwhile, the decentralists envisioned a free industrial society, in which independent local groups would organize and establish laws as they saw fit. After the 1924 split, the IWW saw a decline in membership, but continues to be active today.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library. The accession number associated with this collection is 1950.261.
Some materials were donated by Susan Parker Sherwood at an unknown date. The accession number associated with this gift is NPA.2003.058.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Centralia Massacre, Centralia, Wash., 1919.; Syndicalism -- United States.; Political prisoners -- United States.; Industrial Workers of the World. G.R.U. Branch (New York, N.Y.); Industrial Workers of the World. General Defense Committee; Industrial Workers of the World; Sherwood, Susan Parker
- Series I: General Files, 1905-2005; 1.75 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 2 shared boxes
  - Application for Membership, undated (Box 1)
  - Articles and Newspaper Clippings, 1928-2005, undated (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies, 1969-2005, undated (Box 1)
  - Boston Area Local Branch, undated (Box 1)
  - Canada, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Cartoons, 1925-1987, undated (Box 1)
  - Chicago Branch, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Chicago General Membership Branch, 1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1964-1996, undated (Box 1)
  - Coal Mine Workers Industrial Union, No. 220, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Collective Bargaining, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Conferences, 2005 (Box 1)
  - Fliers and Leaflets, 1971-1990, undated (Box 1)
  - Foodstuff Workers' Industrial Union, No. 460, undated (Box 1)
  - General Defense Committee, 1973-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - General Organization Bulletin, 1987-1994 (Box 1)
  - General Organizing Committee, 1974 (Box 1)
  - General Recruiting Union, 1935 (Box 1)
  - General Referendum Ballot, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Great Britain, 1980-1981 (Box 1)
  - Hawaii, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Health Service Workers, No. 610, undated (Box 1)
  - History/Structure, 1905-1919, undated (Box 1)
  - Industrial Union Manifesto, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 006, Folder 13)
  - Industrial Transportation Project, 1990-2002 (Box 1)
  - Labor History Calendar, 1995-2000 (Box 1)
  - Labor History Calendar (100th Anniversary of the Struggle for the 8-Hour Day), 1986 (Box 1)
  - LeHigh Valley, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Madison (WI), 2011 (Box 1)
  - Membership books, 1906-1949 (Box 2)
  - Metal and Machinery Workers Union, No. 440, 1933, undated (Box 1)
  - New York Branch I, 1971-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - New York Branch II, 1971-1972, undated (Box 1)
  - New York General Membership Branch I, 1973, undated (Box 1)
  - New York General Membership Branch II, 1975 (Box 1)
  - No. 450, undated (Box 1)
  - NY Organizing Committee, 1981-1982, undated (Box 1)
  - One Big Union Job Committee, undated (Box 1)
  - Organizing Manual, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets I, 1905-1999, undated (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 191, Folder 21-22)
  - Pamphlets II, 1979-1989, undated (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets III, undated (Box 1)
  - Preamble and Constitution, 1968-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Publications Relating To, 1918, undated (Box 1)
  - Publishing Bureau, 1918, undated (Box 1)
  - Railroad Workers Industrial Union, No 520, undated (Box 1)
  - Rank-and-File Organizing Committee, undated (Box 1)
  - San Fernando Valley State College Job Branch of 620, 1970, undated (Box 1)
  - Shoe Workers Industrial Union Local 168 - Buccafori Defense Committee, 1911 (Box 1)
  - Songbooks, 1953-1984, undated (Box 1)
  - Starbucks Workers Union, undated (Box 1)
  - Strike Support, 1972, undated (Box 1)
  - Tacoma-Olympia Branch, 1977 (Box 1)
- Series II: New York City Branch, 1905-1976; 1.5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 1 manuscript box
  - Agricultural Workers Industrial Union, 110, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Articles and Newspaper Clippings I, 1918-1971 (Box 1)
  - Articles and Newspaper Clippings II, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Australia and New Zealand General Organizing Committee Bulletin, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Ballot Committee, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies, 1923-1970, undated (Box 1)
  - Brot-Backer Der West Side: Branch 3, Local 46, 1908 (Box 1)
  - Cartoons and Stickers, 1932-1971, undated (Box 1)
  - Centralia Publicity Committee, 1919-1928, undated (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1959-1963, undated (Box 1)
  - Conventions, 1934-1936 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1915-1959, undated (Box 2)
  - Fliers/Leaflets I, 1905-1945, undated (Box 2)
  - Fliers/Leaflets II, 1906-1962, undated (Box 2)
  - General Construction Workers Industrial Union No. 310, 1924 (Box 2)
  - General Defense Committee, 1919-1948, undated (Box 2)
  - General Defense Committee: Defense Bulletin, 1924-1938 (Box 2)
  - General Defense Committee: Defense News Service I, 1922 (Box 2)
  - General Defense Committee: Defense News Service II, 1922-1925 (Box 2)
  - General Defense Committee: General Defense Bulletin, 1941 (Box 2)
  - General Defense Committee: Workers Defense, 1932 (Box 2)
  - General Executive Board, 1922 (Box 2)
  - General Labor Union, 1932 (Box 2)
  - General Office Bulletin, 1923 (Box 2)
  - General Organization Bulletin, 1967 (Box 2)
  - General Recruiting Union, 1966-1967, undated (Box 2)
  - Los Angeles General Membership, undated (Box 2)
  - Marine Transport Workers Industrial Union No. 510, 1936 (Box 2)
  - New York Defense Committee, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Notes, undated (Box 2)
  - One Big Union (Canada), undated (Box 2)
  - One Big Union: Workers' Bulletin, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets I, 1957, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets II, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets III, 1918, undated (Box 2)
  - Paterson Silk Workers Strike, 1913, undated (Box 2)
  - Postcards, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Preamble and Constitution, 1905-1965, undated (Box 2)
  - Publications Bureau, 1918, undated (Box 2)
  - Publications Relating To, 1906-1921, undated (Box 2)
  - Seattle Joint Branches, undated (Box 2)
  - Statement of J.B. Phelan (Political Prisoner), 1919 (Box 2)
  - Ticket (Social and Dance), 1936 (Box 2)
  - Trial Bulletin, 1918 (Box 2)
  - Workers' Defense Union, 1919-1920 (Box 2)